<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Hyperfine Podcast Blog - Shownotes</title><link href="https://zakespley.github.io/Hyperfine/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://zakespley.github.io/Hyperfine/feeds/shownotes.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://zakespley.github.io/Hyperfine/</id><updated>2018-02-02T10:00:00-08:00</updated><entry><title>The Floating Hourglass</title><link href="https://zakespley.github.io/Hyperfine/the-floating-hourglass.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-02T10:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2018-02-02T10:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Zak Espley</name></author><id>tag:zakespley.github.io,2018-02-02:/Hyperfine/the-floating-hourglass.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Derek and Zak discuss a strange video of an hourglass trapped in a tube of water. Sometimes the hourglass floats, and other times it stays put.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;!--CSS -http://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquerymobile/1.4.5/jquery.mobile.min.css ,
JS -  
http://code.jquery.com/jquery-1.11.1.min.js,http://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquerymobile/1.4.5/jquery.mobile.min.js, 
https://maxcdn.bootstrapcdn.com/bootstrap/4.0.0/js/bootstrap.min.js,
https://maxcdn.bootstrapcdn.com/bootstrap/4.0.0/css/bootstrap.min.css   --&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started by looking at the following animation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://i.makeagif.com/media/7-29-2016/Clh8gl.gif"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is very counter intuitive. Though the distribution of mass changes within the hourglass, the total mass and volume is always the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In physics we are taught that for Newton's 2nd Law, &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\sum F_{ext}=ma&lt;/script&gt;, we can treat distributed masses like a point, with all of the forces acting at the center of mass. So it seems that the force of gravity and the buoyant force should always be the same. This would imply that the hourglass either always sinks, or always floats since the sum of the external forces is not changing. The odd feeling that this isn't behaving as expected prompted the podcast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Derek's Hypothesis&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Derek came up with a theory about how the hourglass could wedge itself against the walls of the container due to an unstable equilibrium. We know from the start of the GIF that the hourglass wants to float, and therefore it should always float unless another force is acting on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike Newton's 2nd Law, when we consider the net torque on a body we can not treat it like a point mass. Thus &lt;strong&gt;how&lt;/strong&gt; the mass is distributed will effect the torque. When the sand is in the upper half, the hourglass would like to flip. But since the walls of the cylinder are preventing it from flipping, it gets stuck. The walls add another force to the system, friction. This frictional force holds the hourglass down prevents it from floating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the sand drains to the bottom, the hourglass will right itself vertically, and release itself from the wall. Now the force of friction is gone and the hourglass is free to float again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turn's out, this is the correct answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Zak's Thoughts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a sanity check, Zak created a couple models of the system to see what would happen. In the podcast we ran into problems with our first simple model. Afterwards, Zak realized the problems and the rest is explained below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Two cans, side-by-side&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Setup&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;img src="images/thefloatinghourglass/Hourglass-CansStacked-Forces (2).png" width=500px&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zak started by considering two non-interacting cans submerged in water. The total mass of the system is &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;M&lt;/script&gt; and is held constant. We can magically transfer mass between the cans, but we can't add or subtract from the total amount inside. The can on the right has mass &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;m_T&lt;/script&gt; (T for top as we'll see later) and the can on the left mass &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;m_B&lt;/script&gt; (B for bottom). &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;M&lt;/script&gt; can be expressed as the sum of &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;m_T&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;m_B&lt;/script&gt;. That is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;script type="math/tex; mode=display"&gt;\begin{align}
    M = m_T + m_B \label{eq:mathconv}
\end{align}&lt;/script&gt;
Since the basic unit of mass in this system is the mass volume of water displaced by a single can, &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;m_w&lt;/script&gt;, we should express all masses this way. Thus the total mass will become:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;script type="math/tex; mode=display"&gt;\begin{align}
    M=\kappa m_w \ni \kappa \in \mathbb{R^{+}} \label{eq:kmass}
\end{align}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus we have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;script type="math/tex; mode=display"&gt;\begin{align}
    \kappa m_w = m_T + m_B \label{eq:kmassSum}
\end{align}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since total mass is conserved we will parameterize how much of the total mass is in the top can using a filling factor &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\lambda&lt;/script&gt; such that &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;0 \leq \lambda \leq 1&lt;/script&gt;. When &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\lambda=1&lt;/script&gt;, all of the mass will be in the right can, and none in the left. When &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\lambda=0&lt;/script&gt;, the opposite is true. This means that all the masses are described by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;script type="math/tex; mode=display"&gt;\begin{align}
    m_T &amp;=\lambda M \label{eq:mt} \\
    m_B &amp;= (1-\lambda) M \label{eq:mb}\\
    \kappa m_w &amp;= \lambda\kappa m_w + (1-\lambda)\kappa m_w \label{eq:mass}
\end{align}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\eqref{eq:mass} can be accounted for by combining \eqref{eq:kmass}, \eqref{eq:kmassSum}, \eqref{eq:mt} and \eqref{eq:mb}.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Expectation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are we trying to see with this model? What would tell us if this model describes the floating hourglass of not?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is some way that we can distribute the masses such that when we stack the cans, the forces the put on each other will cancel for a while. Then at some point, when &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\lambda&lt;/script&gt; reaches a certain value, the net force (acceleration) is up. To be worked on....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Intuition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;When do objects float?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start we look at any submerged object (not just the cans, but for any object). If gravity and the buoyant forces are the only two forces acting on the object, and it is neutrally buoyant (that is that it neither wants to sink nor float), then we know the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;script type="math/tex; mode=display"&gt;\begin{align}
    -mg+F&amp;_{Buoy} = 0 \notag \\
    \Rightarrow F_{Buoy}&amp;=mg \label{eq:Buoy1}
\end{align}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the buoyant force is defined as the following, where &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\rho_w&lt;/script&gt; is the density of water (since we are using water) and &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;V&lt;/script&gt; is the volume of the object. More information and teh derivation of the equation can be seen at &lt;a href="https://www.khanacademy.org/science/physics/fluids/buoyant-force-and-archimedes-principle/a/buoyant-force-and-archimedes-principle-article"&gt;Khan Academy's lesson on the buoyant force&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;script type="math/tex; mode=display"&gt;\begin{align}
    F_{Buoy} = \rho_wVg = m_wg \label{eq:Buoy2}
\end{align}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last equality comes from mass being the product of density and volume. Notice though that since it is the density of water and the volume of the object, we get the mass of the water displaced by the object. This is true of any object submerged in water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we substitute \eqref{eq:Buoy2} into \eqref{eq:Buoy1} to get the condition for neutral buoyancy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;script type="math/tex; mode=display"&gt;\begin{align}
    m = m_w \label{eq:buoycond1}
\end{align}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is to say that the object will be neutrally buoyant when its mass is equal to the mass of the volume of water it has displaced. If &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;m &gt; m_w&lt;/script&gt; then that object will sink. If &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;m &lt; m_w &lt;/script&gt; the object will float. (Often times you see this same condition express in terms of densities.) This is summed up in the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;script type="math/tex; mode=display"&gt;
    \left.
    \begin{aligned}
        m = m_w &amp;\Rightarrow \text{Neutrally Buoyant} \\
        m &lt; m_w &amp;\Rightarrow \text{Object Floats} \\
        m &gt; m_w &amp;\Rightarrow \text{Object Sinks}
    \end{aligned} \tag{10} \label{eq:buoycond}
    \right\}
&lt;/script&gt;
For us, this means that one of our cans will float when it has equal to &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;m_w&lt;/script&gt;. This happens for either individual can when it is full and &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\kappa=1&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's look at &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;m_w&lt;/script&gt; from another, more intuitive, light. &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;m_w&lt;/script&gt; is the mass of water displaced by the the can. It can also be thought of as the mass of the can if it were full of water. This is how we will refer to &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;m_w&lt;/script&gt; here on out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What is &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\kappa&lt;/script&gt;?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\kappa&lt;/script&gt; is more specific to our model. It is a scaling that lets us represent the total mass of the system as some amount of cans full of water. i.e. if &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\kappa=\frac{1}{2}&lt;/script&gt; then the total mass is equal to half of the mass of one of the cans filled with water. Kappa can be any real positive number. If &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\kappa= \pi&lt;/script&gt; then the total mass is equal to &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\pi&lt;/script&gt; cans full of water. Using this and our floating conditions should help us get a good footing on what will happen to our system with certain bounds for &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\kappa&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Floating and sinking in our model.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have some idea of what &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\kappa&lt;/script&gt; represents, let's now look at different distributions of mass (different &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\lambda&lt;/script&gt; values), for different total masses (different &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\kappa&lt;/script&gt; values). We can think about what happens as mass moves form the right can to the left, &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\lambda:1\rightarrow0&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\kappa &lt; 1&lt;/script&gt;, then &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;M &lt; m_w&lt;/script&gt; by \eqref{eq:kmass}. If we compare that to our floating conditions, \eqref{eq:buoycond} we see the system should float.  This means that no matter what &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\lambda&lt;/script&gt; is, our system can never sink. Even if all if the mass is in one can or the other, &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\lambda=1&lt;/script&gt; or  &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\lambda=0&lt;/script&gt;, the full can will still be lighter than a can full of water. However we distribute the mass, both cans will float.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\kappa=1&lt;/script&gt; the system will have the same mass as one of the cans full of water. Then while &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\lambda&lt;/script&gt; varies between 1 and 0 mass will start in the right can move to the left. When &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\lambda=1&lt;/script&gt; we will meet our neutral buoyancy condition, \eqref{eq:buoycond1}, for the right can. The left will then went float. Once we move any amount of mass from the right can to the left, &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;0&lt;\lambda&lt;1&lt;/script&gt;, both cans will want to float as each will now have a mass less than &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;m_w&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we consider &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;1&lt;\kappa&lt;2&lt;/script&gt;. When all the mass starts in the right can, we will have &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;m_T &gt; m_w&lt;/script&gt; and thus the can will want to sink. As &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\lambda&lt;/script&gt; decreases and mass is transferred from the right to the left, we will find a point where &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;m_T=m_w&lt;/script&gt;. At this point the right can will be neutrally buoyant and for all &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\lambda&lt;/script&gt; less than this point, the right can will float.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far I have discussed what happens to the right can when &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\kappa &lt; 1&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\kappa = 1&lt;/script&gt;, and &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;1 &lt; \kappa &lt; 2&lt;/script&gt;. As an exercise for the reader, can you determine what will happen to the right can for &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\kappa = 2&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\kappa &gt; 2&lt;/script&gt;. Are there any other special values of &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\kappa&lt;/script&gt; we should care about? Additionally can you go back and determine what will happen with the left can as we very &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\kappa&lt;/script&gt; (I've done some of the work for you)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is an interactive simulation that can help you figure things out. Beneath it is a description of how you might use it to help answer the questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Simulation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id="display"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for="lamVal"&gt;&lt;script type="math/tex; mode=display"&gt;\lambda=&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type="text" id="lamVal" readonly style= "border:0; font-weight:bold; width:2em; margin-bottom:13px; margin-left:5px "&gt;
&lt;div class="col jqslider" id="lambda"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for="kapVal"&gt;&lt;script type="math/tex; mode=display"&gt;\kappa=&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type="text" id="kapVal" readonly style= "border:0; font-weight:bold; width:2em; margin-bottom:13px;"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="col jqslider" id="kappa"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="centered"id="canchart" align="center"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="row"&gt;
    &lt;div class="col"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;$$a_T=\text{blue}$$&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;$$a_B=\text{red}$$&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;$$a_{total}=a_T+a_B=\text{green}$$&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;$$\text{Current } \lambda=\text{yellow}$$ &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Description&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is our setup. You have two cans submerged in water. The red arrow represents the buoyant force, the purple arrow is the force of gravity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two sliders, one for &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\lambda&lt;/script&gt; and the other for &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\kappa&lt;/script&gt;. You can slide them to change the amount of sand that is in either can, or the total amount of sand. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below the sliders is plot of the acceleration of the two cans. In blue you have the acceleration of the right can, and in red the left. Green is the sum of the two accelerations.The yellow line is your current setting for lambda. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you've dialed in your values press the play button and watch what happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;How To Use&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can start by setting the values of &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\lambda&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\kappa&lt;/script&gt; to something you think is interesting. Then use the plot and try to determine what will happen if lambda stays constant. Once you have a guess, press the play button and see what happens. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try walking through different values of &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\kappa&lt;/script&gt; based on what we discussed above. Then for each value of &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\kappa&lt;/script&gt;, vary &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\lambda&lt;/script&gt; to see what changes. Press the refresh button to but the cans back at their starting positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, you can run the hourglass simulation by clicking on the running man. This will start with all the sand in the right (top) can, and transfer it to the left (bottom) can as time proceeds. This is meant to simulate what happens with the hourglass. Is there ever a situation in which the cans behave like the hourglass did?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From our two can setup we can draw some conclusions. Namely, that Newton was right and objects can be treated like point objects. It should appear obvious that this model does not accurately describe the hourglass and what is going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should have found that only when &lt;script type="math/tex"&gt;\kappa&lt;1&lt;/script&gt; did the cans move in the same direction at the same time. For all other situations, the right can starts going down and at some point, will begin to go up while the left can will do the opposite.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="classical mechanics"></category></entry></feed>